You have completed this course assuming you have watched all the lectures in the given order.
So what is next? Sometimes people will ask me via private message that
Hey Vinoth, can you suggest what I should learn next? Something like that.
I have created few courses and I can explain on what basis I created them
so that you can pick the next topic which interests you.
Let's consider an application with microservices architecture here.
We have a bunch of services talking to one another like this.
Let's say we are receiving hundreds of thousands of requests per minute here.
How can we process all these requests more efficiently without launching or before horizontally scaling another instance?
How can we make use of the given CPU or memory properly?
Here we have two options.
One is using Java Virtual Thread.
Java finally after many years they have introduced virtual threads.
Using virtual threads we write synchronous blocking style code.
But Java will do non-blocking I.O for us to process requests more efficiently.
I have a course on that. Check that out.
Another option is developing reactive microservice with Spring Web Flex.
The whole process is done.
This whole reactive paradigm is kind of new.
Different style of programming and reactive programming enables us to do stream-based communication.
It's very hard to achieve with the synchronous blocking style code.
So by using either of these options we can develop one single microservice
which should be capable of processing requests more efficiently.
Microservices are great. Easy to develop, test and deploy.
But when we create multiple microservices and talking to one another like this,
there will be network latency and it will affect the overall application processing time.
How can we improve our back-end communication?
For the back-end communication I can suggest three options.
The one is gRPC created by Google.
They have been using it for years.
It uses protocol buffers and HTTP2 to reduce the network latency.
And they improve the application throughput, response time, etc.
So this is great. You can check this out.
The next one is Rsocket.
It's almost same as this gRPC but it's reactive style.
This one is from Netflix.
This is also great for the back-end communication.
If you like messaging for the asynchronous communication among microservices,
then we can also go with Kafka.
We can compare these but before that let me clarify one thing.
What is stream-based communication?
Traditionally our programming style or our application communication will be like
client will send one request for which the server will give us one response back.
This is how normally we do things.
In the stream-based communication,
it will be like two people talking to one another via phone.
The client will call the server.
Once the connection is established,
they can exchange information continuously.
So we can design interactive application.
Now we can compare the various technologies or options we have for the back-end communication.
If we want restful APIs, we have two options.
We can go with the Spring Web
for the synchronous blocking style code and you will get request and response style programming.
But it's very hard to achieve stream-based communication.
If you want stream-based communication along with the restful APIs,
then we can go with the Spring Webflex.
That is where the reactive programming shines.
If you do not like rest or for the back-end communication,
things do not have to be restful actually.
If you want low latency,
which I would highly encourage,
you to try these for the low latency communication,
we can have gRPC,
which will provide the request and response,
stream-based communication, etc.
Then we have Rsocket, same as this one,
but it's reactive.
gRPC uses HTTP2.
It's a network level 7.
Rsocket is the custom protocol.
It uses network level 5.
So because of that, in theory,
Rsocket should provide better performance
compared to gRPC.
However, gRPC is not really tied to HTTP2.
In the future, they might change the protocol as well.
So you can't go wrong with either of these actually.
Then we have Kafka for the completely even driven asynchronous communication.
What about the communication with the front-end?
We have browser and mobile application, etc.
Talk to the back-end.
So what can we do here?
I can suggest GraphQL here
to avoid some of the challenges with the RESTful APIs
and for efficient data retrieval.
I have one dedicated course on GraphQL.
Check that out.
Particularly for mobile applications,
the gRPC and Rsocket can also work great here
as they are lightweight.
Then what else I can do
to improve my application throughput
and reduce redundant work?
We can also add Redis,
which is high-performance caching layer,
which provides super-fast read-write operations.
We can add Redis in our architecture
to improve the application throughput
and the response time.
It can also provide features like pub-sub messaging,
distributed locking among microservices.
We have to be careful when we design our application
because it is a very complex application.
Anything could happen in the network.
One service might be very slow
or one service might fail suddenly.
The problem in one service should not propagate everywhere.
It is always our responsibility
to design our application to be highly resilient.
There are some techniques, design patterns,
we can follow to develop highly resilient application.
We have done that in this course,
microservices design patterns,
integration and resilient design patterns
for microservices architecture.
What about testing?
I have a course on Selenium,
the running automated UI test via CICD pipeline.
I use Jenkins in this course.
You can check that out if you are interested.
Okay, we have developed our application,
which is scalable, performant, etc.
So what about deployment?
What about service discovery?
Here, I would suggest Docker and Kubernetes.
Docker is a must-know tool if you ask me.
If you have never tried Docker,
you will be amazed how it can increase our productivity
by quickly spinning up the dependent application
like databases or other applications for local development.
It is easy to package, deploy, share applications via Docker.
Kubernetes is for orchestration.
For service discovery,
load balancing, rolling update,
rollback, configuration management,
another super important feature, autoscaling.
We definitely should not want to lock ourselves
with one particular cloud provider like AWS or GCP, etc.
Kubernetes is the way to develop applications
which can provide multi-cloud support.
I have one course on this Kubernetes.
We will learn Kubernetes
in the end, you will see.
In less than 10 minutes,
we will run our application on GCP cloud
without doing much.
Autoscaling, service discovery, etc.
will work just out of the box
with the Kubernetes configuration.
To quickly summarize,
these are the topics for which I have courses for now.
Pause this video if you want to review.
Once you picked up the next topic,
if you go to my profile in this Udemy page,
you will see the courses.
You will see the courses in this Udemy platform.
Then you should be able to find all the courses.
Thanks and I will see you soon.