If you have been watching all the lectures sequentially one by one by this time you must
be comfortable with the virtual threads. Congrats! Now you will definitely want to migrate your
existing application to use virtual threads. We have to take certain steps, we have to
be careful. So that is what this quick lecture is about.
We have only few steps, not a lot. We know that virtual threads are for IOTask only,
not for 100% pure compute task. Here we are not going to get any benefit. So this is where
we are going to get benefit. So if your application has IOTask, yeah definitely you can use virtual
threads. Here it does not make any sense.
Double check your application for synchronized keyword. The Java team said that it is a temporary
issue in the future they might fix. But in Java 21 we have this issue so we have to be
careful if you are planning to use virtual threads. So double check your synchronized
the method etc if you are doing IO operation. In that case you have to use re-end run block.
You have to update your code. There is a very good chance that the third party libraries
they might be using this who knows. So you might want to run your application with this
property to detect the pinned threads. If you see some pinned threads and it is not
because of you, it is because of some library then you will have to see if they are providing
any new updated version for Java 21. In that case you might want to update the dependency
as well. The thread builder is not thread safe but the thread builder is new anyway.
So if you are worrying about the existing application probably it is not applicable.
Thread factory is thread safe. And the executor service if your application is using executor
service definitely you might be using one of these implementation because that is what
we have had so far. But all these implementations they all will pull threads. That is how they
all have been implemented because it is for platform threads and the platform threads
is an expensive resource so it makes sense to pull threads there. But virtual thread
is very cheap and it should not be pulled. So do not pass the thread factory to these
implementation. So we have to use the thread per task executor to use virtual threads.
If we have to limit concurrency etc then we have to use some of them.
Thread local will work with the virtual thread somehow Java team they made it work with the
virtual thread but double check if you really need it to use with the virtual threads. Do
not store expensive object because we can create millions of virtual threads right.
So I would say be extra careful here. The spring team they will use thread local and
they will know how to use etc. So let's not worry about the framework. If you are using
directly in your code somewhere so here you have to be a little bit more careful.