After introducing virtual thread as part of Java 21, for some reason this has become a
common question.
Is reactive programming dead?
First of all we have to understand one thing that people have been saying Java is going
to be dead for 20 years.
Is Java dead?
Java is more than 25 years old and we Java developers we love Java.
The concepts like sealed classes, sealed interfaces, record, record patterns, virtual thread etc.
Other modern programming languages they already have.
Java team they have been trained to add all these things one by one for us.
This virtual thread project, the project Loom was going on for many years.
The main goal of virtual thread is not to compete with reactive programming.
Virtual thread will be helpful to make use of the system resources like CPU more efficiently.
We will also get the non-blocking IO benefits behind the scenes.
Now this is where the question arises that if I can get the non-blocking IO benefit via
virtual thread then why do we need reactive programming?
It should be dead right?
I understand the question but it is wrong to think that the whole point of reactive programming
is to achieve non-blocking IO.
We also have structured concurrency but currently it's in the preview and its goal is different.
Whatever it's trying to solve it's not anything to do with reactive programming.
Then what is reactive programming?
Reactive programming is a programming paradigm, a special implementation of observer design
pattern.
It's based on three pillars.
Building IO, stream based asynchronous communication with back pressure support.
We need reactive programming to build reactive system.
We understand the first point.
Here we do not have any confusion.
In this video we can understand the second and third points by using an application which
I think that it is the perfect example of reactive system.
Before that, Java has already enabled reactive programming by introducing few interfaces
as part of the Java util concurrent package, the Flow class.
We already have few libraries for reactive programming like Reactor, Rx, Java, To, Aca,
Streams etc.
Currently they all use platform threads because that is what we have had before Java 21.
Now as part of Java 21, since we have virtual threads, these libraries they might start
using virtual threads now.
As you see, the Reactor they have already updated to use virtual threads.
As you see now, these libraries they are already going to get the benefit of virtual threads.
So virtual thread is not going to kill reactive programming.
For the past 20-25 years, we have been traditionally programming like client server, request, response.
This is how we see things.
This is how we have been coding.
But if we consider gRPC, RSocket etc. they can be little bit interactive.
If we have used RSocket, you will understand that it does not see that client and server.
It will be seeing this as two different systems talking to one another.
It is something like two people talking over the phone.
The traditional synchronous blocking style code will not be helpful as it does not provide
the necessary tools for this communication.
This is why we need something slightly different which is reactive programming.
Reactive programming is a tool to build reactive system.
Now let's take a look at the second and third points by using one popular application.
That application is chat GPT.
Now I want you to observe this.
I am going to ask a simple question.
Let's see what it does.
As soon as I ask a question, it is trying to give me a response.
In the example what we just saw, the chat GPT took almost 7 seconds to provide me the
full response.
Now let's imagine we do the traditional synchronous blocking style programming.
You ask a question, the answer will be prepared and it might take 7 seconds.
Then we return the answer.
Now think about the user experience.
How it will be?
You ask a question, for the next 7 seconds nothing is going to happen.
Then you get the response.
You are getting right because this is how the traditional programming we are doing actually.
So we prepare the answer and we return the actual object, the T object.
Because of this return type, whoever called this method, they will have to wait for this
method to complete till the answer is returned to the caller.
Now in the reactive programming, when someone calls this method, we do not block the caller.
We immediately return something.
So that something right.
In the reactive programming normally we call that Bublisher.
So the Bublisher you have to imagine this something like a pipe.
So as soon as the method is invoked, we return the Bublisher.
Then we prepare the answer asynchronously.
Then we send the answer via that pipe, as-send-when it's available.
In the traditional programming, you prepare the big answer and you send at once.
In the reactive programming, you send, you can send them as chunks, as-send-when is available.
As-send-when you have something available, you can keep on sending them.
The reactive programming might still take 7 seconds to prepare the answer.
That's fine.
But the idea here is we do not block the caller and we provide something to the caller as-send-when
something is available.
Because of that, it will look responsive.
Now if you check the chat GPD behavior, it didn't take 7 seconds and it didn't give
me the complete response after 7 seconds.
Instead as-send-when something is available, it kept on sending to the screen.
So that we could see under the application look responsive.
Completable feature is not reactive.
It's mainly because it cannot send stream of values.
Completable feature can provide only one value at a time.
You cannot send stream of values.
Now let's come back to chat GPT and I am going to ask the same question and I would
like to show another important feature actually.
So if I hit enter, now it's trying to give me something as-usual.
I say stop and it stopped.
In the second example, I asked the question and chat GPT was giving me the stream of answer.
It did not complete the answer fully.
But as soon as I saw the rest endpoint one example, I realized oh this is how I have
to do.
Okay.
I stopped.
Stop.
Then it stopped.
You are getting right.
Sometimes you might not be interested in the complete response.
The complete response might take 30 seconds, 30 minutes.
Who knows?
So it might keep on sending the response.
However, you are actually satisfied with the partial response.
As soon as you received this response, immediately you are satisfied.
Yeah, this is what I need.
Stop.
So as soon as you say stop, it stopped.
You are getting right.
So you have the ability to stop the execution whenever you like.
If you check the traditional programming, you will get the answer only after 7 seconds
or only after 30 seconds.
So you cannot cancel because you cannot see anything until the answer arrives.
You are getting right.
But on the reactive programming, since we are sending the answer in chunks, the stream-based
communication, if you are already satisfied with the partial response, you can simply
cancel the execution so that this publisher does not have to do unnecessary work.
Let's come back to this one more time.
This time I have a different question to ask.
Show me the first 1000 prime numbers.
This is what I am going to ask.
Let's see what it does.
So it's trying to give me all the prime numbers.
So let's observe this.
If you notice, it stopped at 282 and it did not give me the complete 1000 prime numbers.
Instead, it stopped at 282 and it shows this button saying that should I still continue
generating?
Am I still here?
This is how it behaves actually.
So if I want to see the answer further, I can click on it so that it simply continues
from where it stopped.
And it did not give me all the 1000 up front.
If you sit and silently observe this, it will stop at some point.
Again, it stopped at 538 and if I want to continue, I can continue.
Why I wanted to show that example is mainly because that is what the back pressure is.
For example, in the traditional programming, again we ask a question, we prepare the complete
response, then we provide.
In the reactive programming, since we do the stream based communication, just because the
caller asks, hey, can you generate 1 million items?
The producer does not have to generate all the 1 million items and keep on sending them
one by one.
What if the caller is not using the response we are sending?
So this is what we are saying back pressure that is you keep on generating the response.
If you think that the caller is not using the response or is a slow consumer, the producer
will automatically stop.
That is the back pressure.
So it will not unnecessarily do any work.
The producer will automatically stop when it thinks that the consumer is not consuming
the items.
So this is something we can achieve in reactive programming.
In the traditional programming style, we cannot do that.
So in order for the producer to keep producing the items, the consumer also has to consume
the items at the same rate.
If the consumer is slow, the producer will stop producing and it will do something else.
Then it will start again only when the consumer is making some progress.
In this case, we clicked on the continue generating button.
So we kind of acknowledge or we kind of tell the chat GPT application to keep producing.
Similarly, we have to acknowledge or we have to consume the items so that it will keep
producing.
Reactive programming is a tool to build reactive system.
So it does not have to be like two different methods in a class.
It can be completely two different systems.
The producer could be a database.
So you might want to execute a query for which it might be sending the response as a stream.
You are getting right.
Now if you compare this with the virtual threads and the structured concurrency, definitely
virtual thread is going to help with the non-blocking IOW.
However, virtual thread or the structured concurrency is not going to help with the
back pressure or stream based asynchronous communication.
When we say stream based communication, is this something like a completely even driven
architecture or something like a Kafka streaming?
If you ask like this, no, it does not have to be like that.
We can also use HTTP.
For example, in Spring Web Flex, that is what we use, right?
It's HTTP.
But most of us, we are still using HTTP 1.1, but Spring Web Flex also supports HTTP 2,
the neti.
In the HTTP 2, we can have stream based communication.
HTTP 2 is different, a lot better than HTTP 1.1.
So we can have stream based communication, HTTP 2.