After introducing virtual thread as part of Java 21, for some reason this has become a
common question. Is reactive programming dead?
First of all we have to understand one thing that people have been saying, Java is going
to be dead for 20 years. Is Java dead?
Java is more than 25 years old and we Java developers, we love Java. The concepts like
sealed classes, sealed interfaces, record, record patterns, virtual thread etc. Other
modern programming languages they already have. Java team they have been trying to add
all these things one by one for us.
This virtual thread project, the project Loom was going on for many years. The main goal
of virtual thread is not to compete with reactive programming. Virtual thread will be helpful
to make use of the system resources like CPU more efficiently. We will also get the
non-blocking I O benefits behind the scenes.
Now this is where the question arises that if I can get the non-blocking I O benefit
via virtual thread, then why do we need reactive programming? It should be dead right? I understand
the question but it is wrong to think that the whole point of reactive programming is
to achieve non-blocking I O. We also have structured concurrency but currently it is
in the preview and its goal is different. Whatever it is trying to solve, it is not
anything to do with reactive programming.
Then what is reactive programming?
Reactive programming is a programming paradigm, a special implementation of observer design
pattern. It is based on three pillars. Non-blocking I O, stream based asynchronous communication
with back pressure support.
We need reactive programming to build reactive system. We understand the first point, here
we do not have any confusion. In this video we can understand the second and third points
by using an application, which I think that it is the perfect example of reactive system.
Before that, Java has already enabled reactive programming by introducing few interfaces
as part of the java util concurrent package, the flow class. We already have few libraries
for reactive programming like Reactor, RxJava, to-acca streams etc. Currently they all use
platform threads because that is what we have had before Java 21. Now as part of Java 21,
since we have virtual threads, these libraries they might start using virtual threads now.
As you see, the Reactor, they have already updated to use virtual threads. As you see
now, these libraries, they are already going to get the benefit of virtual threads. So
virtual threads is not going to kill reactive programming.
For the past 20-25 years, we have been traditionally programming like client server, request response.
This is how we see things, this is how we have been coding. But if we consider gRPC,
R socket etc, they can be little bit interactive. If you have used R socket, you will understand
that it does not see that client and server. It will be seeing this as two different systems
talking to one another. It is something like two people talking over the phone. The traditional
synchronous blocking style code will not be helpful as it does not provide the necessary
tools for this communication. This is why we need something slightly different which
is reactive programming. Reactive programming is a tool to build reactive system.
Now let's take a look at the second and third point by using one popular application. That
application is ChatGPT. Now I want you to observe this. I am going to ask a simple question.
Let's see what it does. As soon as I ask a question, it is trying to give me a response.
In the example what we just saw, the ChatGPT took almost 7 seconds to provide me the full
response. Now let's imagine we do the traditional synchronous blocking style programming. You
ask a question, the answer will be prepared and it might take 7 seconds. Then we return
the answer. Now think about the user experience. How it will be? You ask a question, for the
next 7 seconds nothing is going to happen. Then you get the response. You are getting
right? Because this is how the traditional programming we are doing actually. So we prepare
the answer and we return the actual object. The t object. Because of this return type
whoever called this method, they will have to wait for this method to complete till the
answer is returned to the caller. Now in the reactive programming when someone calls this
method we do not block the caller. We immediately return something. So that something right?
In the reactive programming normally we call that publisher. So the publisher you have
to imagine this something like a pipe. So as soon as the method is invoked we return
the publisher. Then we prepare the answer asynchronously. Then we send the answer via
that pipe as and when it is available. In the traditional programming you prepare the
big answer and you send at once. In the reactive programming you send, you can send them as
chunks as and when it is available. As and when you have something available you can
keep on sending them. The reactive programming might still take 7 seconds to prepare the
answer that's fine. But the idea here is we do not block the caller and we provide something
to the caller as and when something is available. Because of that it will look responsive.
Now if you check the chat GPT behavior right? It didn't take 7 seconds and it didn't give
me the complete response after 7 seconds. Instead as and when something is available
it kept on sending to the screen. So that we could see under the application look responsive.
Completable feature is not reactive. It's mainly because it cannot send stream of values.
Completable feature can provide only one value at a time. You cannot send stream of values.
Now let's come back to chat GPT and I am going to ask the same question and I would like
to show another important feature actually. So if I hit enter, now it's trying to give
me something as usual. I say stop and it stopped. In the second example I asked the question
and chat GPT was giving me the stream of answer. It did not complete the answer fully. But
as soon as I saw the REST endpoint one example I realized oh this is how I have to do. I
stopped. When I say stop then it stopped. You are getting right. Sometimes you might
not be interested in the complete response. The complete response might take 30 seconds
30 minutes who knows. So it might keep on sending the response. However you are actually
satisfied with the partial response. As soon as you received this response you immediately
you are satisfied yeah this is what I need. Stop. So as soon as you say stop it stopped.
You are getting right. So you have the ability to stop the execution whenever you like. If
you check the traditional programming you will get the answer only after 7 seconds or
only after 30 seconds. So you cannot cancel because you cannot see anything until the
answer arrives. You are getting right. But on the reactive programming since we are sending
the answer in chunks, it's a stream based communication. If you are already satisfied
with the partial response you can simply cancel the execution so that this publisher
does not have to do unnecessary work. Let's come back to this one more time. This time
I have a different question to ask. Show me the first thousand prime numbers. This is
what I'm going to ask. Let's see what it does. So it's trying to give me all the prime numbers.
So let's observe this. If you notice it stopped at 282 and it did not stop. So it stopped
at 282 and it did not give me the complete thousand prime numbers. Instead it stopped
at 282 and it gives me, it shows this button saying that should I still continue generating.
Am I still here? This is how it behaves actually. So if I want to see the answer further I can
show that it simply continues from where it stopped. But it did not give me all the
thousand up front. If you sit and silently observe this it will stop at some point. Again
it stopped at 538 and if I want to continue I can continue. Why I wanted to show that
example is mainly because that is what the back pressure is. For example in the traditional
programming, again we ask a question, we prepare the complete response, then we provide. In
the reactive programming since we do the stream based communication, just because the caller
asks hey can you generate one million items, the producer does not have to generate all
the one million items and keep on sending them one by one. What if the caller is not
using the response we are sending. So this is what we are saying that, we are saying
back pressure that is you keep on generating the response. If you think that the caller
is not using the response or is a slow consumer, the producer will automatically stop. That
is the back pressure. So it will not unnecessarily do any work. The producer will automatically
stop when it thinks that the consumer is not consuming the items. So this is something
we can achieve in reactive programming. In the traditional programming style we cannot
do that. So in order for the producer to keep producing the items, the consumer also has
to consume the items at the same rate. If the consumer is slow, the producer will stop
producing and it will do something else. Then it will start again only when the consumer
is making some progress. In this case we clicked on the continue generating button right. So
we kind of acknowledge or we kind of tell the chatgpt application to keep producing.
Similarly we have to acknowledge or we have to consume the items so that it will keep
producing. Reactive programming is a tool to build reactive system. So it does not have
to be like two different methods in a class. It can be completely two different systems.
The producer could be a database. So you might want to execute a query for which it
might be sending the response as a stream. You are getting right. Now if you compare
this with the virtual threads and the structured concurrency, definitely virtual thread is
going to help with the non-blocking I O. However virtual thread or the structured concurrency
is not going to help with the back pressure or stream based asynchronous communication.
When we say stream based communication is this something like a completely even driven
architecture or something like a Kafka stream. If you ask like this, no it does not have
to doesn't have to be like that. We can also use HTTP for example in Spring WebFlex that
is what we use right is HTTP. But most of us we are still using HTTP 1.1 but Spring
WebFlex also supports HTTP 2. In the HTTP 2 we can have stream based communication.
HTTP 2 is different lot better than HTTP 1.1 so we can have stream based communication
HTTP 2.