If you have been watching all the lectures sequentially one by one by this time, you must be comfortable with the virtual threads. Congrats!
Now you will definitely want to migrate your existing application to use virtual threads.
We have to take certain steps. We have to be careful. So that is what this quick lecture is about.
We have only few steps, not a lot.
We know that virtual threads are for IOTask only.
Not for 100% pure compute task. Here we are not going to get any benefit.
So this is where we are going to get benefit.
So if your application has IOTask, yeah definitely you can use virtual threads.
Here it does not make any sense.
Check your application for synchronized keyword.
The Java team said that it's a temporary issue.
In the future they might fix. But in Java 21 we have this issue.
So we have to fix it.
But we have to be careful if you are planning to use virtual threads.
So double check your synchronized method etc if you are doing IOOperation.
In that case you have to use reentrant lock.
You have to update your code.
There is a very good chance that the third party libraries, they might be using this.
Who knows.
So you might want to run your application with this property to detect the pinned threads.
If you see some pinned threads.
And it's not because of you.
It's because of some library.
Then you will have to see if they are providing any new updated version for Java 21.
In that case you might want to update the dependency as well.
The thread builder is not thread safe.
But the thread builder is new anyway.
So if you are worrying about the existing application probably it's not applicable.
Thread factory is thread safe.
And the executor service.
If your application is using executor service.
Definitely you might be using one of these implementations.
Because that is what we have had so far.
Right.
So but all these implementations they all will pull threads.
That's how they all have been implemented.
Because it is for platform threads.
And the platform threads is an expensive resource.
So it makes sense to pull threads there.
But virtual thread is very cheap.
And it should not be pulled.
So do not pass the thread factory to these libraries.
So we have to use the thread per task executor to use virtual threads.
If we have to limit concurrency etc.
Then we have to use some of them.
Thread local will work with the virtual thread.
Somehow Java team they made it work with the virtual thread.
But double check if you really need it to use with the virtual threads.
Do not store expensive objects.
Because we can create millions of virtual threads.
Right.
So I would say be extra careful here.
The spring team they will use thread local.
And they will know how to use etc.
So let's not worry about the framework.
If you are using directly in your code somewhere.
So here you have to be little bit more careful.