If we have been watching all the lectures sequentially one by one by this time you must
be comfortable with the virtual threads, congrats.
Now you will definitely want to migrate your existing application to use virtual threads.
We have to take certain steps, we have to be careful, so that is what this quick lecture
is about.
We have only few steps, not a lot.
We know that virtual threads are for Iwo task only, not for 100% pure compute task.
Here we are not going to get any benefit, so this is where we are going to get benefit.
So if your application has Iwo task, yeah, definitely you can use virtual threads.
Here it does not make any sense.
Check your application for synchronizer keyword.
The Java team said that it is a temporary issue.
In the future they might fix, but in Java 21 we have this issue, so we have to be careful
if you are planning to use virtual threads.
So double check your synchronizer, the method etc if you are doing Iwo operation.
In that case you have to use re-endrenedlock.
You have to update your code.
There is a very good chance that the third-party libraries might be using this who knows.
So you might want to run your application with this property to deduct the pin the threads.
If you see some pin the threads and it is not because of you, it is because of some library,
then you will have to see if they are providing any new updated version for Java 21.
In that case you might want to update the dependency as well.
The thread builder is not thread safe, but the thread builder is new anyway.
So if you are worrying about the existing application probably it is not applicable.
Thread factory is thread safe.
And the executive service if your application is using executive service, definitely you
might be using one of these implementation because that is what we have had so far.
So but all these implementations they all will pool threads.
That is how they all have been implemented because it is for platform threads and the platform
thread sets and expensive resource.
So it makes sense to pool threads there.
But virtual thread is very cheap and it should not be pooled.
So do not pass the thread factory to these implementation.
So we have to use the thread per task executor to use virtual threads.
If we have to limit concurrency etc.
Then we have to use some of them.
Thread local will work with virtual thread somehow Java team they made it work with virtual
thread.
But double check if you really need it to use with the virtual threads do not store expensive
object because we can create millions of virtual threads right.
So I would say be extra careful here.
The spring team they will use thread local and they will know how to use etc.
So let us not worry about the framework.
If you are using directly in your code somewhere.
So here you have to be a little bit more careful.