You have completed this course assuming you have watched all the lectures in the given
order.
So what is next?
Sometimes people will ask me via private message that hey Vinod can you suggest what I should
learn next?
Something like that.
I have created few courses and I can explain on what basis I created them so that you can
pick the next topic which interests you.
Let's consider an application with the microservices architecture here.
We have a bunch of services talking to one another like this.
Let's say we are receiving hundreds of thousands of requests per minute here.
How can we process all these requests more efficiently without launching or before horizontally
scaling another instance?
How can we make use of the given CPU or memory properly?
Here we have two options.
One is using Java Virtual Thread.
Java finally after many years they have introduced virtual threads.
Using virtual threads we write synchronous blocking style code but Java will do non-blocking
IO for us to process requests more efficiently.
I have a course on that.
Check that out.
Another option is developing reactive microservice with the Spring WebFlex.
The whole reactive paradigm is kind of new.
Different style of programming and reactive programming enables us to do stream based
communication.
It's very hard to achieve with the synchronous blocking style code.
So by using either of these options we can develop one single microservice which should
be capable of processing requests more efficiently.
Microservices are great, easy to develop, test and deploy.
But when we create multiple microservices under talking to one another like this, there
will be network latency and it will affect the overall application processing time.
How can we improve our backend communication?
For the backend communication I can suggest three options.
The one is GRPC created by Google.
They have been using it for years.
It uses protocol buffers and HTTP2 to reduce the network latency and improve the application
throughput, response time etc.
So this is great.
You can check this out.
The next one is R-Socket.
It's almost same as this GRPC but it's reactive style.
This one is from Netflix.
This is also great for the backend communication.
If you like messaging for the asynchronous communication among microservices then we
can also go with Kafka.
We can compare these but before that let me clarify one thing.
What is stream based communication?
Traditionally our programming style or our application communication will be like client
will send one request for which the server will give us one response back.
This is how normally we do things.
In the stream based communication it will be like two people talking to one another
via phone.
The client will call the server.
Once the connection is established they can exchange information continuously.
So we can design interactive application.
Now we can compare the various technologies or options we have for the backend communication.
If we want RESTful APIs we have two options.
We can go with Spring Web for the synchronous blocking style code and you will get request
and response style programming but it's very hard to achieve stream based communication.
If we want stream based communication along with RESTful APIs then we can go with Spring
Web Flex.
That is where the reactive programming shines.
If we do not like REST or for the backend communication things do not have to be RESTful
actually.
If we want low latency which I would highly encourage you to try these for the low latency
communication we can have gRPC which will provide the request and response stream based
communication etc.
Then we have R-Circuit same as this one but it's reactive.
gRPC uses HTTP2 it's a network level 7.
R-Circuit is the custom protocol.
It uses network level 5 so because of that in theory R-Circuit should provide better
performance compared to gRPC.
However gRPC is not really tied to HTTP2.
In the future they might change the protocol as well.
So you can't go wrong with the either of these actually.
Then we have Kafka for the completely even driven asynchronous communication.
What about the communication with the front end?
We have browser and mobile application etc.
Talk to the backend.
So what can we do here?
I can suggest GraphQL here to avoid some of the challenges with the RESTful APIs and
for efficient data retrieval.
I have one dedicated course on GraphQL.
Check that out.
Especially for mobile applications the gRPC and R-Circuit can also work great here as
they are lightweight.
Then what else I can do to improve my application throughput and reduce redundant work.
We can also add Redis which is high performance caching layer which provides super fast read
write operations.
We can add Redis in our architecture to improve the application throughput and the response
time.
It can also provide features like pub sub messaging, distributed locking among microservices.
We have to be careful when we design our application.
Anything could happen in the network.
One service might be very slow or one service might fail suddenly.
The problem in one service should not propagate everywhere.
It is always our responsibility to design our application to be highly resilient.
There are some techniques design patterns we can follow to develop highly resilient
application.
I have documented that in this course microservices design patterns, integration and resilient
design patterns for microservices architecture.
What about testing?
I have a course on Selenium, the running automated UI test via CI-CD pipeline.
I use Jenkins in this course.
You can check that out if you are interested.
Ok, we have developed our application which is scalable, performant etc.
So what about deployment, service discovery.
Here I would suggest Docker and Kubernetes.
Docker is a must know tool if you ask me.
If you have never tried Docker, you will be amazed how it can increase our productivity
by quickly spinning up the dependent application like databases or other applications for local
development.
It is easy to package, deploy, share applications via Docker.
Kubernetes is for orchestration, for service discovery, load balancing, rolling update,
rollback, configuration management, another super important feature, auto scaling.
We definitely should not want to lock ourselves with one particular cloud provider like AWS
or GCP etc.
Kubernetes is the way to develop applications which can provide multi-cloud support.
I have one course on this Kubernetes.
We will learn Kubernetes.
In the end you will see in less than 10 minutes we will run our application on GCP cloud without
doing much.
Auto scaling, service discovery etc. will work just out of the box with the Kubernetes configuration.
To quickly summarize, these are the topics for which I have courses for now.
Pause this video if you want to review.
Once you picked up the next topic, if you go to my profile in this Udemy platform, then
you should be able to find all the courses.
Thanks and I will see you soon.
Thank you.